{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Strain energy is the", "opta": "energy stored in a body when strained within elastic limits", "optb": "energy stored in a body when strained upto the breaking of a specimen", "optc": "maximum strain energy which can be stored in a body", "optd": "proof resilience per unit volume of a material", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A vertical column has two moments of inertia (i.e. Ixx and Iyy ). The column will tend to buckle in the direction of the", "opta": "axis of load", "optb": "perpendicular to the axis of load", "optc": "maximum moment of inertia", "optd": "minimum moment of inertia", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The neutral axis of the cross-section a beam is that axis at which the bending stress is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "minimum", "optc": "maximum", "optd": "infinity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Euler's formula holds good only for", "opta": "short columns", "optb": "long columns", "optc": "both short and long columns", "optd": "weak columns", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The object of caulking in a riveted joint is to make the joint", "opta": "free from corrosion", "optb": "stronger in tension", "optc": "free from stresses", "optd": "leak-proof", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A steel bar of 5 mm is heated from 15\u00b0 C to 40\u00b0 C and it is free to expand. The bar Will induce", "opta": "no stress", "optb": "shear stress", "optc": "tensile stress", "optd": "compressive stress", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A body is subjected to a tensile stress of 1200 MPa on one plane and another tensile stress of 600 MPa on a plane at right angles to the former. It is also subjected to a shear stress of 400 MPa on the same planes. The maximum normal stress will be", "opta": "400 MPa", "optb": "500 MPa", "optc": "900 MPa", "optd": "1400 MPa", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two shafts 'A' and 'B' transmit the same power. The speed of shaft 'A' is 250 r.p.m. and that of shaft 'B' is 300 r.p.m. The shaft 'B' has the greater diameter.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A thick cylindrical shell having ro and ri as outer and inner radii, is subjected to an internal pressure (p). The maximum tangential stress at the inner surface of the shell is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stress induced in a body, when suddenly loaded, is __________ the stress induced when the same load is applied gradually.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "one-half", "optc": "twice", "optd": "four times", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a beam, as shown in the below figure, the maximum deflection is .", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the slenderness ratio for a column is 100, then it is said to be a __________ column.", "opta": "long", "optb": "medium", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A masonry dam may fail due to", "opta": "tension in the masonry of the dam and its base", "optb": "overturning of the dam", "optc": "crushing of masonry at the base of the dam", "optd": "any one of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to prevent crushing of masonry at the base of the dam, the maximum stress should be __________ the permissible stress of the soil.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a body is subjected to two equal and opposite pushes, as a result of which the body tends to reduce its length, the stress and strain induced is compressive.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bending moment at a point on a beam is the algebraic __________ of all the moments on either side of the point.", "opta": "sum", "optb": "difference", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum diameter of the hole that can be punched from a plate of maximum shear stress 1/4th of its maximum crushing stress of punch, is equal to (where t = Thickness of the plate)", "opta": "t", "optb": "2t", "optc": "4t", "optd": "8t", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two closely coiled helical springs 'A' and 'B' are equal in all respects but the number of turns of spring 'A' is half that of spring 'B' The ratio of deflections in spring 'A' to spring 'B' is", "opta": "1/8", "optb": "1/4", "optc": "1/2", "optd": "2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The deformation per unit length is called", "opta": "tensile stress", "optb": "compressive stress", "optc": "shear stress", "optd": "strain", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A thin cylindrical shell of diameter (d) and thickness (t) is subjected to an internal pressure (p). The ratio of longitudinal strain to volumetric strain is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the torsion equation  the term J/R is called", "opta": "shear modulus", "optb": "section modulus", "optc": "polar modulus", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Strain resetters are used to", "opta": "measure shear strain", "optb": "measure linear strain", "optc": "measure volumetric strain", "optd": "relieve strain", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The torque transmitted by a solid shaft of diameter (D) is (where \u03c4 = Maximum allowable shear stress)", "opta": "x \u03c4 x D3", "optb": "x \u03c4 x D3", "optc": "x \u03c4 x D3", "optd": "x \u03c4 x D3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a rectangular beam is loaded transversely, the maximum compressive stress is developed on the", "opta": "top layer", "optb": "bottom layer", "optc": "neutral axis", "optd": "every cross-section", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a beam, as shown in the below figure, when the load W is applied in the centre of the beam, the maximum deflection is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The point of contraflexure is a point where", "opta": "shear force changes sign", "optb": "bending moment changes sign", "optc": "shear force is maximum", "optd": "bending moment is maximum", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The simply supported beam 'A' of length l carries a central point load W. Another beam 'B' is loaded with a uniformly distributed load such that the total load on the beam is W. The ratio of maximum deflections between beams A and B is", "opta": "5/8", "optb": "8/5", "optc": "5/4", "optd": "4/5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum stress produced in a bar of tapering section is at", "opta": "smaller end", "optb": "larger end", "optc": "middle", "optd": "anywhere", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The energy stored in a body when strained within elastic limit is known as", "opta": "resilience", "optb": "proof resilience", "optc": "strain energy", "optd": "impact energy", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In compression test, the fracture in cast iron specimen would occur along", "opta": "the axis of load", "optb": "an oblique plane", "optc": "at right angles to the axis of specimen", "optd": "would not occur", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bending stress in a beam is __________ section modulus.", "opta": "directly proportional to", "optb": "inversely proportional to", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When shear force at a point is zero, then bending moment is __________ at that point.", "opta": "zero", "optb": "minimum", "optc": "maximum", "optd": "infinity", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum bending moment for the beam shown in the below figure, lies at a distance of __________ from the end B.", "opta": "l/2", "optb": "l/3", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a bar is cooled to - 5\u00b0C, it will develop", "opta": "no stress", "optb": "shear stress", "optc": "tensile stress", "optd": "compressive stress", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The limit of eccentricity is based upon no tension condition.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to know whether a column is long or short, we must know its slenderness ratio.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A composite shaft consisting of two stepped portions having spring constants k1 and k2 is held between two rigid supports at the ends. Its equivalent spring constant is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "k1+k2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Resilience is the", "opta": "energy stored in a body when strained within elastic limits", "optb": "energy stored in a body when strained upto the breaking of the specimen", "optc": "maximum strain energy which can be stored in a body", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the depth is kept constant for a beam of uniform strength, then its width will vary in proportional to (where M = Bending moment)", "opta": "M", "optb": "M", "optc": "M2", "optd": "M3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A concentrated load is one which", "opta": "acts at a point on a beam", "optb": "spreads non-uniformly over the whole length of a beam", "optc": "spreads uniformly over the whole length of a beam", "optd": "varies uniformly over the whole length of a beam", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the tearing efficiency of a riveted joint is 50%, then ratio of rivet hole diameter to the pitch of rivets is", "opta": "0.20", "optb": "0.30", "optc": "0.50", "optd": "0.60", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rectangular beam 'A' has length l, width b and depth d. Another beam 'B' has the same length and depth but width is double that of 'A'. The elastic strength of beam 'B' will be __________ as compared to beam A.", "opta": "same", "optb": "double", "optc": "four times", "optd": "six times", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a simple bending of beams, the stress in the beam varies", "opta": "linearly", "optb": "parabolically", "optc": "hyperbolically", "optd": "elliptically", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A beam supported at its both ends is not a simply supported beam.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stress at which the extension of the material takes place more quickly as compared to the increase in load, is called", "opta": "elastic limit", "optb": "yield point", "optc": "ultimate point", "optd": "breaking point", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The strain energy stored in a solid circular shaft subjected to shear stress (\u03c4) is (where C = Modulus of rigidity for the shaft material)", "opta": "x Volume of shaft", "optb": "x Volume of shaft", "optc": "x Volume of shaft", "optd": "x Volume of shaft", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When two main plates are kept in alignment butting each other and riveted with cover plate on both sides of the main plates with two rows of rivets in each main plate, the joint is known as __________ double cover butt joint.", "opta": "single riveted", "optb": "double riveted", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Whenever a material is loaded within elastic limit, stress is __________ strain.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "directly proportional to", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A load which is spread over a beam in such a manner that it varies uniformly over the whole length of abeam is called uniformly __________ load.", "opta": "distributed", "optb": "varying", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct?", "opta": "The energy stored in a body, when strained within elastic limit is known as strain energy.", "optb": "The maximum strain energy which can be stored in a body is termed as proof resilience.", "optc": "The proof resilience per unit volume of a material is known as modulus of resilience.", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}